so
how to let go of your intentions
or when you hear buddhism or people
letting go of circles
let go let go what do you let go of what
when people say how do i let go when do
they ask that question
do they ask that question were they at
the peak of their happiness
and when the life is good do they ask
how to let go of this
no so the question's always asked when
there's something bothering you
and you're overwhelmed when you're
overwhelmed yeah when something's not
going away
when you can't help but keep revolving
on something that's unpleasant
so then oh i want to let go so you let
go by by
by recognizing that you are suffering
now because you haven't let go before
so the experience of of discomfort
displeasure you know loss of the loved ones or
you know loss of the loved ones or
something like that that you can't let
go of now
so the suffering of that is because you
haven't let go before
and um and that's why they say like you
have to stop trying to get rid of that
suffering because that's not what
letting go means
letting go means really developing
wisdom in regard to the
the nature of not being able to hold
things in the first place
see because if you were truly holding
the dear one or something they would
have not
passed they would have not changed you
would have not been experienced in
suffering you would have been in control
but people don't see that when things
are good because they don't look for it
they don't look for the recognition that
things are not in your control
even when they are good because if you
were to not forget
that things are not in your control you
wouldn't need to let go as much
because when things change against your
will or the way you don't want them to
be well you are already
implicitly aware they were never in your
control to begin with
so see you already let it go to that
extent
but it's when people don't want to see
that when things are good
when things are happy and things are
bright they fully develop a belief that they
they fully develop a belief that they
are in control of what they own what
they possess
um who they love who they're with but
then things change
as as you know they will but you would
ignore them that they will
and now you want to let go but really
now you just want to not suffer
the consequences of pain as a result of
you holding things blindly so it's not a
question to
never engage with the world because
things will change
it's just to never lose perspective in
regard to that which is subject to
change which is everything around you including
which is everything around you including
yourself
so that would mean letting go it's not
something you do
letting go is understanding that you
could not have held
things in the first place don't just
reflect on things we say about letting go when
on things we say about letting go when
when there is discomfort and whether it
is pain what is reminder of it
but do it at the peak of your happiness
as i say when everything is fine
everything is going your way
be aware that it could it could have not
been that way and it won't be in that
way always
so that's like you know slight kind of
uneasiness in regards to it but that
uneasiness is the gateway to that right
perspective of
recognizing the true meaning of
furniture that they would have talked
about amnesia means subject to change doesn't
amnesia means subject to change doesn't
mean changing all the time
means subject to change that's that's
against your will outside of your scope
of your control
you are subject to it as well
so understanding a niche understanding
being subject to change means
letting go means preventing yourself
from holding blindly
and that's already where letting go is
but yeah often you'll just let go just
letting go
is not a matter of choice even holding
is not a matter of choice
it's basically the result of whether you
have perspective in regard to
what is subject to change or you're
ignoring that that is subject to change so if
that that is subject to change so if
you're ignoring that things are subject
to change
the things that are not in your control
fundamentally you're holding
even if you don't think i will hold this
dearly you are already making this dear
to you
and you're holding it blindly if you're
not ignoring that things are subject to
change so you're consciously making effort oh
so you're consciously making effort oh
look this is my dog my pet i had it my
whole life
i didn't i'm just giving an example
he's like yeah his life can end
my life can end that's that's the most
natural thing
but i don't want to think about it only
when it happens
and now pretend that it will never
happen and just let's talk about
something else
means i am ignoring the basic
crude obvious reality of things being
subject to change
that is against my will and because of
that i'm holding on to him not because i look
i'm holding on to him not because i look
after him
because i feed him i must be attached no
but if i don't have perspective in his
in him being subject to change
me being subject to change oh that's how
i'm holding even if i don't feed him
even if i don't pet him i am actually
attached to it
in other words because i don't have
perspective the same
family members whatever possessions
wealth same health things you take for granted
same health things you take for granted
you take for granted by ignoring
that these things are subject to change
because it's it's kind of disconcerting
to think about it so you think you can
avoid it
by ignoring it but then you pray price
when things do change
in your effect and then you want to let
go but that's that's just the result of
everything else you've been holding
wrongly before
so how do i let go then should we be
reformulators like
how do i not lose perspective in regard
to that
which is subject to change things around
me people
that's anything that's dear to me my
ownership my possessions how do i not
lose perspective well by making effort
to think
about these things rightly even you know
set a time of day like half an hour and
just contemplate how
things are subject to change and when if
you feel anxious here allow that feeling
to manifest
because that is the feeling of the world
that you're in speaking of recognition
well that's the that's yeah exactly
recognizing the
the true nature of things it's not going
to be pleasant
initially to the mind that up to that
point has been making all the effort to
ignore the nature of change and so on so if
the nature of change and so on so if
somebody is asking the question how to
let go means at least to that extent
they have some sort of recognition of
their responsibility and their own
suffering so how do i let go
so i don't suffer so it's it's a good
thing but it's it's
it's far from being sufficient how do i
let go but this is how you let go
okay now i let go and now i'm fine
suffering you're experiencing kind of
not letting go is the result
it's kind of the symptom of an
underlying problem that you've been
ignoring which is
things are subject to change and you
don't want to admit that yourself
because it's unpleasantly felt as simple
as that
so you let go by admitting these things
to yourself by
contemplating them and by enduring the
unpleasantness of it when it arises
because actually you realize you have a
choice now are they going to endure
those kind of mild anxieties and concern on
kind of mild anxieties and concern on
account of yeah things could change
and i will not ignore this or you're
gonna pretend it's not there and then be
pretend it's not there and then be
completely crushed when things do change
against your will and then oh how do i
let go
you know lose your mind with grief and
so on
so don't wait for that
to to prompt you to think about letting
go
yeah that's so that detachment and that
ease that
it comes from understanding that things
are substituting to change
so that will come from it you don't have
to
exactly you have to do it like oh this
is how do i become detached
you become detached by seeing that you
could not have been attached to it in
the first place not the way you believed
it
and the only way to see that it's not
like i just make a decision i'm not
attached is to contemplate
that which will prevent you to be
attached the way you are
like you cannot be attached to your pets
or a loved one or possessions
if you don't forget that can be taken
away at any given
second so it doesn't matter what you do
this is the ultimate context it's
subject to change that's against my will
that's truly a nietzsche that's what
people when they heard it will talk about a
when they heard it will talk about a
nietzsche they were often shocked and
scared initially and then those who had enough
initially and then those who had enough
composure so oh actually okay yeah
this is worth developing the words
that's the true freedom then
developing your mind in regard to things
that are subject to change
so if you do then not if you do make the
effort and sustain the perspective that
yeah my dear pet can be taken away at
any given time
that perspective will prevent you to
become blindly carelessly
obliviously attached to it
and when it does when it does leave or
when you leave or something happens
uh there will not be as much of a shock
to the system then it's experiencing
yeah because it is truly out of your hands
because it is truly out of your hands
so the grief will be like seriously
seriously dampened and obviously if
you've truly developed
understanding of nature there will be no
grief but i'm talking more like with people
but i'm talking more like with people
you know who are not monks and so on
committed to this practice 24 7.
it's still a useful thing you know being
aware of that of the fact that things are
of that of the fact that things are
subject to change it's a it's a quite a
useful superpower even in life that you
can develop
it keeps you more resilient more patient
more stable
um more basically um
impermeable to like because sometimes
things might change quickly into one and
then the other one
or unpleasant pleasant unpleasant and
pleasant and you will still not
you will still be able to sustain some
sort of composure in regard to it which
most people wouldn't
which means your well-being your
contentment will be less affected
even as a layperson so it's always
useful to to have that authentic recognition of
to to have that authentic recognition of
yeah things are subject to change but it
needs to be also done on that personal
level especially when it comes to the buddhist
especially when it comes to the buddhist
practice people here in each and it's
it's often just taken in this abstract
sense yes everything is
subject to change modern science have
shown everything is constantly changing
and people think about a nature in those
completely impersonal terms
that's not a niche and each is finding
that which is dear to you
and contemplating that to be subject to
change and see how indifferent you're going to
and see how indifferent you're going to
stay if you start thinking that
and that's then you're saying if i if i
work through this that's where the
freedom is that's truly then how you
will not suffer
even with your dearest you know family
members pets friends whatever change you die or
pets friends whatever change you die or
inevitably things will happen
your mind will not doesn't mean you will
not perceive what has happened
or know the significance of it just
means you will not be as affected by it
because you never really lost
perspective in regard to that which is inevitable
in regard to that which is inevitable
sickness all the age and death one way
or the other
quickly or slow doesn't matter it's
inevitable